[
   {
      "question":"The Konyak, Gaddi and Tharu tribes / ethnic people are found in which of the following states respectively?",
      "optionA":"Kerala, Haryana, Bihar",
      "optionB":"Nagaland, Himachal Pradesh, Tamil Nadu",
      "optionC":"Nagaland, Jammu & Kashmir, Uttarakhand",
      "optionD":"Assam, Punjab, Karnataka",
      "correctAns":"Nagaland, Jammu & Kashmir, Uttarakhand"
   },
   {
      "question":"With reference to Rainfed Agriculture in India, consider the following statements:\n1.India is largest among the rainfed agricultural countries of the world in terms of both extent and value of produce \n2.The benefits of Green Revolution could not reach to the Rainfed areas\n3.Cotton, maize and soyabean are the major crops of the rainfed areas of India\nWhich among the above observations are correct?",
      "optionA":"Only 1 & 2",
      "optionB":"Only 2 & 3",
      "optionC":"Only 1",
      "optionD":"1,2 & 3",
      "correctAns":"1,2 & 3"
   },
   {
      "question":"With reference to the availability of coal in India,which among the following is / are correct observations?\nMost of India’s coal production comes from the Gondwana\nMost of India’s coal is of Bituminous type\nSelect the correct option from the codes given below:",
      "optionA":"Only 1",
      "optionB":"Only 2",
      "optionC":"Both 1 & 2",
      "optionD":"Neither 1 nor 2",
      "correctAns":"Both 1 & 2"
   },
   {
      "question":"Consider the following rivers':\n1. Narmada\n2. Damodar\n3. Tapti\nWhich among the above flow in rift valleys?",
      "optionA":"Only 1",
      "optionB":"Only 1 & 2",
      "optionC":"Only 1 & 3",
      "optionD":"1, 2 & 3",
      "correctAns":"1, 2 & 3"
   },
   {
      "question":"How the intensive farming is different from extensive farming?\nWhile intensive farming results in maximum output per unit of land','production per unit of land is low in extensive farming\nWhile extensive farming is not found in India','Intensive farming is common in high grain producing states of India\nSelect the correct option from the codes given below':",
      "optionA":"Only 1",
      "optionB":"Only 2",
      "optionC":"Both 1 & 2",
      "optionD":"Neither 1 nor 2",
      "correctAns":"Only 1"
   },
   {
      "question":"With reference to Rainfed Agriculture in India'\nconsider the following statements:\n1.  India is largest among the rainfed agricultural countries of the world in terms of both extent and value of produce. \n2. The benefits of Green Revolution could not reach to the Rainfed areas\nCotton,maize and soyabean are the major crops of the rainfed areas of India\nWhich among the above observations is / are correct?",
      "optionA":"Only 1 & 2",
      "optionB":"Only 2 & 3",
      "optionC":"Only 1",
      "optionD":"1, 2 & 3",
      "correctAns":"1, 2 & 3"
   },
   {
      "question":"Consider the following departments/ministries':'\nMinistry of Personnel,Public Grievances and Pensions\nDepartment of Atomic Energy\nDepartment of Space\nWhich of the above is/are under the direct charge of the Prime Minister of India?",
      "optionA":"1 Only",
      "optionB":"1 and 3 Only",
      "optionC":"2 and 3 Only",
      "optionD":"1, 2 and 3",
      "correctAns":"1, 2 and 3"
   },
   {
      "question":"Consider the following statements':\n1. The first sign of an El Niño is a rise in air pressure over the Indian Ocean,'Indonesia',and Australia\n2. ENSO is connected with worldwide fishing problems\n\nWhich among the above statements is / are correct?",
      "optionA":"Only 1",
      "optionB":"Only 2",
      "optionC":"Both 1 & 2",
      "optionD":"Neither 1 nor 2",
      "correctAns":"Both 1 & 2"
   },
   {
      "question":"Where in India you will find substantial coral reef formations?\nGulf of Mannar\nGulf of Katch\nAndaman and Nicobar\nLakshadweep Islands\nSelect the correct option from the codes given below':",
      "optionA":"1 & 2",
      "optionB":"2 & 3",
      "optionC":"2, 3 & 4",
      "optionD":"1, 2,3 & 4",
      "correctAns":"1, 2,3 & 4"
   },
   {
      "question":"Consider the following observations about the southern slopes and northern slopes of Himalayas':\n1. Southern slopes are covered with thick vegetation,\nwhile the northern slopes are generally barren\n2. The snowline is lower on the northern slopes than on southern slopes\nWhich among the above observations is/ are correct?",
      "optionA":"Only 1",
      "optionB":"Only 2",
      "optionC":"Both 1 & 2",
      "optionD":"Neither 1 nor 2",
      "correctAns":"Only 1"
   },
   {
      "question":"With reference to the rock formation in India\n'the Deccan Trap is exposed in which of the following states?\nMaharashtra\nGujarat\nUttar Pradesh\nTamil Nadu\nSelect the correct option from the codes given below':",
      "optionA":"Only 1 & 2",
      "optionB":"Only 1",
      "optionC":"Only 1, 2 & 3",
      "optionD":"1, 2,3 & 4",
      "correctAns":"Only 1, 2 & 3"
   },
   {
      "question":"Which of the following is / are correct statements about the north-east monsoon?\nIt blows from land to sea\nIt comes between October to December\nIt brings 60% of the annual rainfall in coastal Tamil Nadu\nSelect the correct option from the codes given below:",
      "optionA":"Only 1 & 2",
      "optionB":"Only 2 & 3",
      "optionC":"Only 1 & 3",
      "optionD":"1, 2 & 3",
      "correctAns":"1, 2 & 3"
   },
   {
      "question":"In context with the Monsoon winds,consider the following statements:\nThey are generally regular and equally distributed winds\nThey show a complete reversal of direction during a year\nThey are generally orographic in nature\nWhich among the above statements is / are correct?",
      "optionA":"Only 1 & 2",
      "optionB":"Only 2 & 3",
      "optionC":"Only 1 & 3",
      "optionD":"1, 2 & 3",
      "correctAns":"Only 2 & 3"
   },
   {
      "question":"Most coral reefs across the world would perish if the surrounding water temperature goes above 31°C. However, the coral reefs in Persian Gulf can withstand temperature up to 35°C. What may be the reason(s) for the same?\nCoral reefs of Persian Gulf use different genetic mechanism when compared to corals reefs of other water bodies.\nWater in the Persian Gulf is less polluted than other water bodies of the world.\nSelect the correct code from options given below:",
      "optionA":"Only 1",
      "optionB":"Only 2",
      "optionC":"Both 1 & 2",
      "optionD":"Neither 1 nor 2",
      "correctAns":"Only 1"
   },
   {
      "question":"Consider the following rivers:\nTons\nBetwa\nKen\nWhich of the above is/are tributary of Yamuna?",
      "optionA":"2 and 3 Only",
      "optionB":"1 and 2 Only",
      "optionC":"1 and 3 Only",
      "optionD":"1, 2 and 3",
      "correctAns":"1, 2 and 3"
   },
    {
     "question":"Dogri language is spoken majorly in which of the following states of India?",
     "optionA":"Odisha",
     "optionB":"Jammu & Kashmir",
     "optionC":"Assam",
     "optionD":"Meghalaya",
     "correctAns":"Jammu & Kashmir"
   },
   {
     "question":"Which among the following are the classical languages of India?\n1. Tamil\n2. Sanskrit\n3. Kannada\n4. Telegu\nChoose the correct option from the codes given below :",
     "optionA":"1 & 2",
     "optionB":"2 & 4",
     "optionC":"1, 2 & 4",
     "optionD":"1, 2, 3 & 4",
     "correctAns":"1, 2, 3 & 4"
   },
   {
     "question":"As per the census 2011, which one of the following is the correct ascending sequence of States with regard to percentage of urban population?",
     "optionA":"Goa-Mizoram-Maharashtra-Kerala",
     "optionB":"Maharashtra-Kerala-Mizoram-Goa",
     "optionC":"Mizoram-Goa-Maharashtra-Kerala",
     "optionD":"Tamil Nadu-Mizoram-Goa-Maharashtra",
     "correctAns":"Maharashtra-Kerala-Mizoram-Goa"
   },
   {
     "question":"What type of settlement is found among the Tharu tribe of the Tarai region?",
     "optionA":"Compact",
     "optionB":"Hamlet",
     "optionC":"Scattered",
     "optionD":"Dispersed",
     "correctAns":"Hamlet"
   }
]